<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Briefe principles of religion, for the exercise of youth: done by Christopher Watson</title>
            <author>Watson, Christopher, d. 1581.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25110</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119561</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854768</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854768</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20212</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20212)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 341:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Briefe principles of religion, for the exercise of youth: done by Christopher Watson</title>
                  <author>Watson, Christopher, d. 1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Hugh Singleton, dwelling in Creede lane, neere vnto Ludgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:20212:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20212:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>BRIEFE PRIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of religion, for <hi>the exerciſe of youth: <hi>done by Christopher Watſon.</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Emaund.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How waſt thou created?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The firſte parte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnations</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſwere.</speaker>
               <p>By the hand of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>He is almightie, creator of all things, incomprehenſible, inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, eternal, preſeruer and gouernour of heauen and earth. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why did he create thee?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>To ſerue him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What ſeruice requireth hee of thee?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Obedience to his lawes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which are they?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>God ſpake all theſe wordes:</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1</hi> Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but me.<note place="margin">Exod. 21.10. the 18.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any grauen Image, nor the likeneſſe of any thing that is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue,
<pb facs="tcp:20212:2"/> or in the earth beneath, nor in the water vnder the earth: thou ſhalt not bow downe to them nor worſhip them.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3</hi> Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lorde thy God in vaine.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> Remember that thou kéepe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the Saboth day.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5</hi> Honour thy father &amp; mother.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> Thou ſhalt doe no murther.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7</hi> Thou ſhalt not commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9</hi> Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10</hi> Thou ſhalt not deſyre thy neighbours houſe: thou ſhalt not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet thy neighbours wife, nor his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, nor his Maide, nor his Oxe, nor his Aſſe, nor any thing that is thy neighbours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Art thou bounde to obſerue theſe precepts, in thought worde and deede?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, for if I breake but one of them in thought, once onely in all my lyfe, I ſhall be guiltie of eternal death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is eternall death then the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
<pb facs="tcp:20212:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> of breaking theſe ſtatutes?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Yea.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doeſt thou keepe them?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>No, nor no man liuing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then thou graunteſt thy ſelf, with all men worthye of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure and eternall damnation.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Yea trulye, I feele Gods wrath, &amp; ſee hell to be my proper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and the fruites of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>* <hi>De.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How ſhalt thou eſcape gods wrath and this damnation?</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The ſecond declareth our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie by Chriſt.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Onely by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How ſhall he ſaue thee?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he being God and man, hath ſuffered al the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t due for my ſinnes, and fulfilled the law.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shall all men be ſaued by Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>No, none but ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue effectually in him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who beleeue thus in him?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>They onelie whiche aſſure themſelues that all his ſufferinges was for them, and ſo trauell morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the fleſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20212:3"/>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who aſſures thee of this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>The holy ghoſt works it by hearing the word preached.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Declare the effect of thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Beléeue in God the Father almighty, maker of heauen &amp; earth. And in Ieſus Chriſt his only ſonne our Lord. Which was conceaued by the holye Ghoſt, borne of the Virgin Mary. Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnder Ponce Pilate, was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified dead and buried. Hee diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into hell. The thirde day hee roſe againe from the dead. He aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into heauen, &amp; ſitteth on the right hande of God the father almightye. From thence he ſhall come to iudge the quick and the dead. I beleeue in the holy ghoſt. The holy Catholyke Church. The Communion of ſaints. The forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the body, and the lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting. Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is thy faith perfect aſſoone as thou beleeueſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>No, but encreaſeth continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:20212:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> by hearing the worde preached, with vſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sacraments &amp; praiers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many Sacramentes be there?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Two, Baptiſme and the Lordes ſupper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What meaneſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> by Baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>It declareth the waſhing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of my ſinnes by Chriſtes bloud, and my new birth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then without this ſacrament none can aſſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay not ſo, Gods grace is not tyed to outwarde ſignes: we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue his promiſe, &amp; therefore doubt not, but the children of the faithfull are ſaued, which dye before they be baptiſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What thinkeſt thou by the Lordes Supper?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>I beléeue, that as my body is nouriſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread there broken, &amp; wine powred foorth, that euen ſo my ſoule is nouriſhed ſpirituallye by Chriſtes body broken, &amp; bloud ſhed for the remiſſion of my ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are all, named Chriſtians, fit to receaue this ſacrament?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20212:4"/>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>No, none but ſuch as are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to diſcerne the Lords body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>* <hi>De.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The thirde our duty to God for all his benefits.</note>
                  <hi>Thou ſaydeſt, prayer was a help to encreaſe faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, for it aſſures me that I ſhall haue all that I aſke in Chriſtes name, according to Gods word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What praieſt thou for?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>For ſuch things as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde hath taught me, <hi>Sayings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>OVr Father whiche art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, halowed hee thy name, Thy kingdome come. Thy wyll be done in earth, as it is in heauen. Giue vs this day our day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread. And forgiue vs our treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as we forgiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that treſpaſſe againſt vs. And lead vs not into te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. But deliuer vs from euil. For thine is the kingdom, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power, &amp; the glory, for euer &amp; euer. Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doeſt rhou pray to god one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not to the ſaintes?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, for prayer is due to god onely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Art y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not bound to God for this thy wonderful creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; deliuery from eternal death?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20212:4"/>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, ſo I account my ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What duties craues he at thy hands for the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>To ſerue &amp; honour him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely, according to his word: which I purpoſe to do, as he by his holy ſpirit ſhall enable mée, knowing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to none but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elect, which labor according to their meaſure in refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming themſelues, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion that Chriſt hath performed al their duties, &amp; diſcharged their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, in which holy work, God giue me ſtrength <hi>(for Chriſtes ſake)</hi> to labour all the dayes of my lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euen ſo. And God encreaſe thy faith, to the full aſſurance of thy ſaluation in CHRISTE. <hi>God ſaue our Queene Elizabeth.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>PRINTED AT LONDON, by Hugh Singleton, dwelling in <hi>Creede lane, neere vnto Ludgate.</hi> 1581.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="privilege">
            <p>Cum priuilegio.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Hugh Singleton, of his rebus and a tun or barrel, after McKerrow 127, with the motto arranged in a surrounding square as in McKerrow 250</figDesc>
                  <q>GOD IS MY HELPER.</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
